In 2006, Steve Jobs approached Intel CEO
Paul Otellini with an offer. Intel would
produce the chips for Apple's upcoming
product, the iPhone. But, Intel refused.
Of course, we know the rest of the
story. But, why did Intel say no? And
what did they do when they realized the
scale of their mistake?
What's even more interesting is the
company that replaced Intel that now
rules not just smartphones, but the
entire tech and doesn't have to
manufacture anything.
To understand this meeting and this
entire story, we have to look at Intel
CEO Paul Otellini. By pretty much all
accounts, a good CEO. He didn't yell and
scream. He never dictated. He never
asked me to come in on a Sunday. He
never asked me to stay late on a Friday.
But, he had his way of getting you to
rise to the occasion. Intel generated
more revenue during his 8-year tenure as
CEO than it did during the rest of the
company's 45-year history. Of course, he
was inheriting tech's golden goose,
Intel, and inflation plays a part here.
But, he had been a wildly successful in
making a profit machine. Tuning the
machine that is Intel happened very well
under his watch.
They've grown revenues a ton and margins
are higher than they used to be. And
that word is the key to this story,
margins. Intel's president after Paul
Otellini, Renee James, said, "He's a
super low-key guy. He's not a Steve
Jobs. He's not a Bill Gates. But, his
contribution has been just as big." And
speaking of Steve Jobs, Apple and Intel
were on about as good terms as you could
get. They would be developing and
supplying the new Core x86 chips for
Macs. To Steve Jobs, Intel seemed like
the perfect fit for their next big
product, the iPhone. So, he approached
Intel with another proposition. They
would manufacture chips for this new
product. But, what he might not have
expected was the reply. Intel was
totally uninterested in mobile. And
around this time, they made another big
decision. Intel had a product called
XScale specializing in mobile chips.
>> [music]
>> Little did Intel know, this could have
been a golden ticket for the future.
But, there was a problem. They'd been
pouring money into XScale for almost 10
years. They had spent over 10 billion
dollars and nothing much came of it.
Palm Trios, pocket PCs from Compaq, MP3
players, a few hits, but mostly duds.
Compared to the PC x86 chips,
>> [music]
>> there was a big difference between the
two. Margins. On average, Intel's chips
cost $40 to produce,
>> [music]
>> but the x86 chips would sell for
hundreds of dollars. But, that didn't
work for mobile devices, which had a
selling price lower than these x86
chips. Intel could only sell these for
less than 100. Intel wasn't exactly
beating down Apple's door to supply it
with a few million $30 ARM chips that
would cost it many millions to develop
and manufacture.
Paul turned down Apple. Not only that,
in June 2006, it sold XScale to Marvell
Technology Group
>> [music]
>> and redeployed about 16,000 employees.
They were pulling out of mobile. It just
didn't seem worth it. That and no one
really foresaw how big the iPhone would
become. The thing you have to remember
is that this was before the iPhone was
introduced and then no one knew what the
iPhone would do. At the end of the day,
there was a chip that they were
interested in that they wanted to pay a
certain price for and not an equal more.
>> [music]
>> And that price was below our forecasted
cost. I couldn't see it. It wasn't one
of those things you can make up on
volume. And
>> [music]
>> in hindsight, the forecasted cost was
wrong and the volume was 100x what
anyone thought. To make matters worse,
deep down, Paul knew this was the wrong
move.
On paper, it made sense. The margins
were awful and they had just sold off
their mobile product family.
So many times in my career, I've ended
up making decisions with my gut and I
should have followed my gut. My gut told
me to say yes.
And oh boy, was his gut right.
But, if not Intel, who did Apple go with
for their iPhone?
Well, it's a bit ironic.
Without knowing it, Intel had created
their own nightmare. But, unfortunately,
modern tech today is also a nightmare.
Everything you do isn't just tracked,
but sold. Most of us think, "Yeah, I get
it. Zuckerberg is watching me." But, we
forget the worst players in the
pipeline, your internet service
provider. They can literally see
everything, not just the websites, but
how long you spend, what you search,
even your smart device behavior.
Government studies have proven this and
even though they promised they won't
sell your data, they use a sneaky trick
to transfer it to others to be monetized
by them. But, it doesn't have to be this
way. Stick it to your ISP with
ProtonVPN.
Proton masks your IP address and
connection to stop your ISP from
tracking you and knowing what you're up
to. ProtonVPN has a strict no-logs
policy. They keep nothing on you, which
is verified by independent auditors.
Plus, they're Europe-based and operate
outside US jurisdiction, allowing them
to uphold strict privacy standards. But,
not only is it more private, ProtonVPN
is just a better web experience. It has
an integrated ad blocker and it lets you
access regionally blocked content like
streaming services and news articles.
And you can still watch shows, movies,
and sports in 4K without buffering. And
their high-speed server network offers
speeds up to 10 GB per second. That's
insanely fast. Many streaming sites are
beginning to catch on to VPNs, though
not Proton. It has a stealth function,
which disguises your VPN connection,
making it especially hard to block.
ProtonVPN has over 20,000 servers in
over 140 countries and supports all
major devices, even Apple TV or Fire TV.
Click the link below to protect your
privacy. Try ProtonVPN today and stick
it to your ISP using my link.
protonvpn.com/logicallyanswered
It comes with up to a 70% discount.
Thank you to Proton for sponsoring our
video. Apple soon turned to Samsung to
produce their chips. Funny, right?
iPhone chips being produced by Samsung.
But, that's not the important part.
Samsung wasn't designing them. They
would just manufacture the chips. The
real powerhouse was a company called ARM
Holdings and this company is key, not
only to this story, but to the entire
world of mobile. ARM would soon become
Intel's biggest rival. But first, some
context. ARM Holdings, the British
company, owns the license to the ARM
chip architecture. ARM chips weren't
powerful, but they were cheap, generated
less heat, and used less power.
Excellent for battery-powered devices.
ARM chips were everywhere, in
practically every mobile phone and
tablet, and even the Game Boy. Not
because they were the fastest, but
because they were the best fit. The
original deal with Intel would have been
to produce ARM-based chips because ARM
doesn't make anything themselves. They
own the license to the ARM architecture.
So, whenever companies like Qualcomm,
Samsung, or Apple use their
architecture, ARM gets a cut of every
chip shipped. Billions of them. ARM is
more a royalties collection company than
a chip company. But, the strangest part
is that ARM was co-founded by Apple
in a partnership with Acorn. Apple
wanted a new chip architecture for the
MessagePad in 1994.
And it wasn't successful. Then, when
Apple was near bankruptcy, Jobs sold
their stake in ARM to stay alive. Then,
the ARM architecture took off thanks to
Nokia and was now dominating the entire
mobile industry. So, the first iPhone
had ARM chips produced by Samsung and of
course, it was a wild success. But,
Apple had a problem. At this point, they
didn't have an in-house custom chip
team. They had actually laid them off in
2005. So, their work with Samsung wasn't
the best.
Not having their own chip design experts
in-house made for very poor
communication with Samsung, which is why
the A1 processor in the iPhone wasn't
quite what they wanted, although it was
exactly what they'd asked for. In other
words, mostly Apple's fault, not
Samsung's. So, they formed a new team
and began designing their own chips.
iPhones got better and better, but they
were still using ARM architecture, which
means still paying a license to ARM
Holdings. Around this time, Intel began
to wake up. They saw how big the iPhone
was and now how massive smartphones
were. More expensive phones meant
potentially better margins, but most of
all, huge scale. The volume was 100x
what anyone thought. Smartphones and
tablets were exploding. But, PCs were
starting to slow down in those core
market. So, Intel thought maybe it's not
too late.
Intel and in particular Paolo Dell'Erba
really wanted to get back in the game,
but they wanted to use x86, the
architecture used by basically the whole
computing world in PCs.
But,
there was a problem.
ARM was simply better for mobile. It was
far more power efficient. If Intel could
introduce a type of x86 chip to mobile
and make it less power hungry, the
software could be compatible with PCs.
They could dominate mobile, tablets,
PCs, notebooks, everything. So, in 2008,
Intel built something new.
Atom.
It was x86, but extremely compact and
energy efficient. And Intel was making
huge strides, just like ARM.
But, Intel had a lot of work to do to
win customers over. In particular,
Apple.
ARM and Intel are on a collision course.
What happens next could determine the
shape of the computing industry for
years to come.
Stories like these shape the history of
tech, yet many people don't know they
exist. Business is full of crazy
decisions and fascinating stories, and
you can learn a lot from them.
We post these kinds of stories all the
time. So, subscribe. We're almost at a
million and it would mean the world.
Intel was ready for war. They made a
deal with TSMC to allow customers to
make their own products based on Atom
cores. And Intel had something else
going for it. It's absurdly deep
pockets.
Atom doesn't have to be an overnight
success in the device market, as long as
Intel can prop it up with sales from its
lucrative PC and server lines.
ARM employs fewer than 1,800 people, and
at $3 billion, its market capitalization
is a mere fraction of Intel's.
But, there was a problem.
Intel forgot what the market actually
needed. x86 wasn't really a good fit for
mobile.
No one cared about compatibility with
PCs.
What the market really needed was
ultra-low power, cheap mobile chips.
Chips you can make tons of and quickly.
Billions of them.
Atom wasn't that. Well, sort of.
Atom could have matched ARM on power
consumption and even beat some models.
The bigger problem was low-power,
integrated, and most of all, cheap
chips.
Intel's business was built around
high-margin chips, chips they made
themselves in a very specific
environment. They control the
architecture, design, manufacturing, and
the process technology.
Great for PCs, but mobile needed cheap
chips.
ARM had designed chips and used Samsung
and TSMC to make them faster and cheaper
than Intel could.
In 2003, Intel shipped its billionth
[music]
x86 chip after being in the game for
decades. But, in 2009, in the midst of
the fight for mobile, ARM shipped 2.8
billion processors in just 1 year.
Plus, there were plenty more problems.
Intel's process technology leadership
couldn't save the company's mobile
division because it wasn't designed to
do so. Smartphone and the tablet OEMs
wanted devices with integrated LTE
radios. Intel didn't have them.
Even the Sofia partnership with the TSMC
never came to market, apparently because
Intel couldn't secure enough volume to
kickstart production.
Intel was trying to push x86 into
mobile, and not only did it not fit,
they couldn't keep up with ARM chips.
Despite a promising start, Atom and
Intel's entire mobile division was
collapsing. The winner was ARM.
And in a very ironic turn of events,
Apple wasn't interested in Intel's
[clears throat] Atom. After Samsung,
they had seen the power of ARM and in
particular designing their own chips,
aka Apple silicon.
Tim Cook even said Apple has a long-term
strategy of owning and controlling the
primary technologies behind the products
we make.
About a decade later, Apple dropped
Intel x86 from their Macs, too. And
guess which architecture they switched
to?
That's right. Intel had lost and ARM had
won. And unlike Intel, ARM didn't even
make a damn chip.
If Intel had said yes all those years
ago, they might be a major mobile player
today, though not in x86, in the ARM
architecture.
I don't think they could have ever
replaced that ecosystem, but they could
have still been a part of it.
And now, they're moving into producing
ARM chips for others, just almost 20
years too late.
But, I do feel bad for Paolo. He seems
like a good leader who made one wrong
decision. Unfortunately, an extremely
important one.
To quote Paolo one last time, at the end
of the day, the best transistors win, no
matter what you're building, a server or
a phone.
Today, nearly every phone and the tablet
uses ARM processors. Apple products,
phones, tablets, notebooks, Chromebooks,
all run on ARM architecture.
To be fair, nobody realized how massive
the iPhone would be. Some of the most
successful people on Earth scoffed at
it.
Paolo isn't the only one who lacks some
foresight. I mean, even Steve Jobs sold
Apple's stake in ARM.
But, if you ever have any regrets, at
least you didn't turn down the iPhone.
AMD has a similar story of missteps in
the past. But now, they're doing better
than ever.
Check out this video to learn more. But
until then,
I'm Harry, and I'll see you guys on the
next one.